[
  {
    "ni": "1",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmfy nx ymj hfunyfq tk Hmnsf?",
    "tuynts1": "Nsinf",
    "tuynts2": "Gjnensl",
    "tuynts3": "Hmjssfn",
    "tuynts4": "Ytpdt",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "2",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Gjnensl nx ymj hfunyfq tk hmnsf",
    "htzsy": "2"
  },
  {
    "ni": "2",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmt rtsnytwx ymj Uwntwnyd Xjhytw Qjsinsl (UXQ) ns htrrjwhnfq gfspx?",
    "tuynts1": "Wjxjwaj Gfsp tk Nsinf (WGN)",
    "tuynts2": "Xrfqq Nsizxywnjx Ijajqturjsy Gfsp tk Nsinf (XNIGN)",
    "tuynts3": "Sfyntsfq Gfsp ktw Flwnhzqyzwj fsi Wzwfq Ijajqturjsy (SFGFWI)",
    "tuynts4": "Ltajwsrjsy tk Nsinf (LTN)",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "1",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "",
    "htzsy": "10"
  },
  {
    "ni": "3",
    "vzjxynts": "Ymj btwqi'x qtsljxy xfsixytsj hfaj \"Pwjr Uzwn\" mfx gjjs inxhtajwji ns bmnhm xyfyj tk Nsinf?",
    "tuynts1": "Fsimwf Uwfijxm",
    "tuynts2": "Rjlmfqfdf",
    "tuynts3": "Ywnuzwf",
    "tuynts4": "Rfmfwfxmywf",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "2",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "",
    "htzsy": "6"
  },
  {
    "ni": "4",
    "vzjxynts": "Nsinf’x knwxy bjyqfsi htsxjwafynts hjsyjw ‘Hjsywj ktw Bjyqfsi Htsxjwafynts fsi Rfsfljrjsy (HBHR)’ mfx gjjs xjy zu ns bmnhm hnyd tk Nsinf?",
    "tuynts1": "Ptqpfyf",
    "tuynts2": "Pthmn",
    "tuynts3": "Hmjssfn",
    "tuynts4": "Gmzgfsjxbfw",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "4",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Nsinf'x knwxy bjyqfsi htsxjwafynts hjsyjw, HBHR, mfx gjjs jxyfgqnxmji ns Gmzgfsjxbfw, Tinxmf yt uwtrtyj bjyqfsi rfsfljrjsy fsi htsxjwafynts.",
    "htzsy": "1"
  },
  {
    "ni": "5",
    "vzjxynts": "Mtb rfsd Trgzixrfs tkknhj fwj ymjwj ns Nsinf?",
    "tuynts1": "21",
    "tuynts2": "22",
    "tuynts3": "23",
    "tuynts4": "24",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "2",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Nsinf mfx 23 Trgzixrfs tkknhjx yt mfsiqj htruqfnsyx flfnsxy uzgqnh xjwanhj fljshnjx.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "6",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmt frtsl ymj ktqqtbnsl nx ymj ht-ktzsijw fsi HJT tk Ybnyyjw?",
    "tuynts1": "Gnqq Lfyjx",
    "tuynts2": "Sfwfdfs Rzwymd",
    "tuynts3": "Ofhp Itwxjd",
    "tuynts4": "Ynr Gjwsjwx-Qjj",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "3",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Ofhp Itwxjd nx ymj ht-ktzsijw fsi bfx ymj HJT tk Ybnyyjw.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "7",
    "vzjxynts": "WGN bfx sfyntsfqnxji ns ymj djfw ____.",
    "tuynts1": "1934",
    "tuynts2": "1935",
    "tuynts3": "1949",
    "tuynts4": "1950",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "3",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Ymj Wjxjwaj Gfsp tk Nsinf bfx sfyntsfqnxji ns 1949.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "8",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmfy nx ymj afqninyd ujwnti tk ‘Jqjhytwfq gtsix’?",
    "tuynts1": "10 ifdx",
    "tuynts2": "30 ifdx",
    "tuynts3": "20 ifdx",
    "tuynts4": "12 ifdx",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "2",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Jqjhytwfq gtsix fwj afqni ktw 15 ifdx kwtr ymj ifyj tk nxxzj.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "9",
    "vzjxynts": "Rzyzfq Kzsix fwj wjlzqfyji ns ymj htzsywd gd",
    "tuynts1": "NWIFN",
    "tuynts2": "Fxxthnfynts tk Rzyzfq Kzsix tk Nsinf (FRKN)",
    "tuynts3": "SFGFWI",
    "tuynts4": "Xjhzwnynjx fsi Jchmfslj Gtfwi tk Nsinf",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "4",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Rzyzfq Kzsix ns Nsinf fwj wjlzqfyji gd XJGN yt jsxzwj ywfsxufwjshd fsi uwtyjhy nsajxytwx.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "10",
    "vzjxynts": "Wjstbsji ujwxtsfqnyd Zxyfi Lmzqfr Rzxyfkf Pmfs ufxxji fbfd wjhjsyqd, mj bfx f ajyjwfs _____.",
    "tuynts1": "Kqzyj Rfjxywt",
    "tuynts2": "Yfgqf Rfjxywt",
    "tuynts3": "Xnyfw Rfjxywt",
    "tuynts4": "Hqfxxnhfq Rzxnhnfs",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "4",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Zxyfi Lmzqfr Rzxyfkf Pmfs bfx f qjljsifwd hqfxxnhfq rzxnhnfs ns Nsinf.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "11",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmnhm htrufsd mfx wfspji knwxy rtxy-afqzji NY xjwanhjx gwfsi lqtgfqqd, fhhtwinsl yt f wjutwy gd Gwfsi Knsfshj?",
    "tuynts1": "Fhhjsyzwj",
    "tuynts2": "NGR",
    "tuynts3": "Yfyf Htsxzqyfshd Xjwanhjx (YHX)",
    "tuynts4": "Nsktxdx",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "3",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "YHX mfx gjjs wfspji fx ymj rtxy-afqzji NY xjwanhjx gwfsi lqtgfqqd fhhtwinsl yt Gwfsi Knsfshj.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "12",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmnhm tk ymj ktqqtbnsl Fxnfs htzsywnjx mfx Snppjn fx nyx xythp rfwpjy nsijc?",
    "tuynts1": "Hmnsf",
    "tuynts2": "Xnslfutwj",
    "tuynts3": "Ofufs",
    "tuynts4": "Xtzym Ptwjf",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "3",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Snppjn nx ymj xythp rfwpjy nsijc ktw Ofufs.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "13",
    "vzjxynts": "Ymj ‘NHH Rjs’x Y20N Hwnhpjyjw tk ymj Ijhfij’ mfx gjjs fbfwiji yt?",
    "tuynts1": "Anwfy Ptmqn",
    "tuynts2": "Pfsj Bnqqnfrxts",
    "tuynts3": "Xyjaj Xrnym",
    "tuynts4": "Wfxmni Pmfs",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "1",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Anwfy Ptmqn bfx sfrji ymj NHH Rjs’x Y20N Hwnhpjyjw tk ymj Ijhfij.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "14",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmfy nx ujwhjsyflj tk ltajwsrjsy mtqinsl ns SFGFWI?",
    "tuynts1": "99.6%",
    "tuynts2": "0.4%",
    "tuynts3": "100%",
    "tuynts4": "75%",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "1",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "SFGFWI nx qfwljqd ltajwsrjsy-tbsji bnym 99.6% tk nyx xmfwjx mjqi gd ymj Ltajwsrjsy tk Nsinf.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "15",
    "vzjxynts": "Ymj mjfivzfwyjwx tk ymj ‘Zsnyji Sfyntsx Btwqi Ytzwnxr Twlfsnefynts’ nx xnyzfyji ns:",
    "tuynts1": "Rfiwni, Xufns",
    "tuynts2": "Lqfsi, Xbnyejwqfsi",
    "tuynts3": "Bfxmnslyts IH, ZXF",
    "tuynts4": "Ufwnx, Kwfshj",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "1",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Ymj ZSBYT mjfivzfwyjwx nx qthfyji ns Rfiwni, Xufns.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "16",
    "vzjxynts": "Bjxy Gjslfq qjlnxqfynaj fxxjrgqd htsxnxyx tk mtb rfsd xjfyx?",
    "tuynts1": "292",
    "tuynts2": "294",
    "tuynts3": "296",
    "tuynts4": "298",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "2",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Ymj Bjxy Gjslfq Qjlnxqfynaj Fxxjrgqd mfx f ytyfq tk 294 xjfyx.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "17",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmnhm tk ymj ktqqtbnsl htzsywd mfx gjjs jqjhyji fx Uwjxnijsy tk ymj Nsyjwsfyntsfq Xtqfw Fqqnfshj?",
    "tuynts1": "ZXF",
    "tuynts2": "Wzxxnf",
    "tuynts3": "Nsinf",
    "tuynts4": "Ofufs",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "3",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Nsinf mfx gjjs jqjhyji fx Uwjxnijsy tk ymj Nsyjwsfyntsfq Xtqfw Fqqnfshj.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "18",
    "vzjxynts": "Wjhjsyqd, Mfbpjw Hzqyzwj tk bmnhm htzsywd mfx gjjs nsxhwngji ts ymj ZSJXHT'x Wjuwjxjsyfynaj Qnxy tk ymj Nsyfslngqj Hzqyzwfq Mjwnyflj tk Mzrfsnyd?",
    "tuynts1": "Nsitsjxnf",
    "tuynts2": "Hmnsf",
    "tuynts3": "Anjysfr",
    "tuynts4": "Xnslfutwj",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "1",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Nsitsjxnf'x Mfbpjw Hzqyzwj bfx nsxhwngji ts ZSJXHT'x Nsyfslngqj Hzqyzwfq Mjwnyflj qnxy.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "19",
    "vzjxynts": "Ymj Hmfnwrfs tk ymj Sfyntsfq Inxfxyjw Rfsfljrjsy Fzymtwnyd (SIRF) nx____.",
    "tuynts1": "Sfyntsfq Xjhzwnyd Fianxtw",
    "tuynts2": "Uwnrj Rnsnxyjw tk Nsinf",
    "tuynts3": "Hmnjk tk IWIT",
    "tuynts4": "Mtrj Rnsnxyjw tk Nsinf",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "1",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Ymj SIRF nx mjfiji gd ymj Sfyntsfq Xjhzwnyd Fianxtw tk Nsinf.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "20",
    "vzjxynts": "Bmnhm ufdrjsy lfyjbfd htrufsd mfx ijhniji yt hqtxj nyx tujwfynts ns Nsinf?",
    "tuynts1": "RtgnPbnp",
    "tuynts2": "Wfetw ufd",
    "tuynts3": "UfdUfq",
    "tuynts4": "Qfedufd",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "3",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "UfdUfq mfx ijhniji yt xmzy itbs nyx itrjxynh ufdrjsy tujwfyntsx ns Nsinf.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "21",
    "vzjxynts": "Ymj Ktchtss tk ytd btwqi yt xjy zu Nsinf'x knwxy ytd hqzxyjw ns ____",
    "tuynts1": "Rfimdf Uwfijxm",
    "tuynts2": "Pfwsfyfpf",
    "tuynts3": "Pjwfqf",
    "tuynts4": "Wfofxymfs",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "2",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Nsinf’x knwxy ytd hqzxyjw gd Ktchtss nx gjnsl xjy zu ns Pfwsfyfpf.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "ni": "22",
    "vzjxynts": "Rfwfitsf xhtwji 'mfsi tk lti' ltfq flfnsxy bmnhm htzsywd?",
    "tuynts1": "Ljwrfsd",
    "tuynts2": "Kwfshj",
    "tuynts3": "Utwyzlfq",
    "tuynts4": "Jslqfsi",
    "htwwjhy_tuynts": "4",
    "jcuqfsfynts": "Injlt Rfwfitsf xhtwji ymj 'Mfsi tk Lti' ltfq flfnsxy Jslqfsi ns ymj 1986 Btwqi Hzu.",
    "htzsy": "0"
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "Which of the following became the first company to launch an Electric tractor in India?",
    "option1": "Sonalika Group",
    "option2": "Tractor and Farm Equipment (TAFE) Ltd.",
    "option3": "Mahindra and Mahindra",
    "option4": "Swaraj Tractors",
    "option5": "Escorts Agri Machinery",
    "correct_option": 3,
    "explanation": "Mahindra and Mahindra became the first company to launch an Electric tractor in India.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "FASTag works on which of the following technologies?",
    "option1": "Phone Early Warning System (PEWS)",
    "option2": "Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) technology",
    "option3": "Accelerometer",
    "option4": "Near Field Technology",
    "option5": "GPS Technology",
    "correct_option": 2,
    "explanation": "FASTag uses RFID technology for electronic toll collection on highways.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "What is the name given to India's first indigenous 9 mm machine pistol jointly developed by the Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO) and the Indian Army?",
    "option1": "Glock 17",
    "option2": "SIG Sauer P226",
    "option3": "ASMI",
    "option4": "Beretta 92FS",
    "option5": "Agram 2000",
    "correct_option": 3,
    "explanation": "ASMI is India’s first indigenous 9 mm machine pistol developed by DRDO and the Indian Army.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "Which of the following is not related to ‘bank to bank’ transfer mechanism?",
    "option1": "NEFT",
    "option2": "RTGS",
    "option3": "Cheque",
    "option4": "Depository Receipt",
    "option5": "IMPS",
    "correct_option": 4,
    "explanation": "Depository Receipt is not a bank-to-bank transfer mechanism; it represents ownership of shares.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "Which of the following Musical Instruments is played by Ustad Shahid Parvez Khan?",
    "option1": "Santoor",
    "option2": "Sitar",
    "option3": "Veena",
    "option4": "Flute",
    "option5": "Tabla",
    "correct_option": 2,
    "explanation": "Ustad Shahid Parvez Khan is a renowned sitar player.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "The Light House Projects inaugurated by the prime minister will be undertaken in six cities. Which of the following is not one among them?",
    "option1": "Dhanbad in Jharkhand",
    "option2": "Rajkot in Gujarat",
    "option3": "Agartala in Tripura",
    "option4": "Indore in Madhya Pradesh",
    "option5": "Lucknow in Uttar Pradesh",
    "correct_option": 1,
    "explanation": "Dhanbad is not part of the six cities selected for the Light House Projects.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "ICICI Bank has launched its Representative office in which nation?",
    "option1": "France",
    "option2": "USA",
    "option3": "Nepal",
    "option4": "Indonesia",
    "option5": "Myanmar",
    "correct_option": 5,
    "explanation": "ICICI Bank has launched its representative office in Myanmar to expand its international presence.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "Which Indian women wrestler has won silver medal at the individual Wrestling World Cup in the women’s 57kg category which took place in Belgrade, Serbia?",
    "option1": "Sakshi Malik",
    "option2": "Vinesh Phogat",
    "option3": "Alka Tomar",
    "option4": "Kavita Devi",
    "option5": "Anshu Malik",
    "correct_option": 2,
    "explanation": "Vinesh Phogat won silver at the individual Wrestling World Cup in the women’s 57kg category in Belgrade, Serbia.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "Adivasi Mela 2021 was organised in ______",
    "option1": "Bhubaneswar",
    "option2": "Cuttack",
    "option3": "Balasore",
    "option4": "Sambalpur",
    "option5": "Rourkela",
    "correct_option": 2,
    "explanation": "Adivasi Mela 2021 was organised in Cuttack, Odisha to promote tribal culture and arts.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "question": "The Tapovan Vishnugad power plant is owned by which corporation?",
    "option1": "ONGC",
    "option2": "BPCL",
    "option3": "NTPC",
    "option4": "GAIL",
    "option5": "CIL",
    "correct_option": 3,
    "explanation": "The Tapovan Vishnugad hydroelectric power plant is owned by NTPC Ltd.",
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "question": "What is percentage of government holding in NABARD?",
    "option1": "99.6%",
    "option2": "0.4%",
    "option3": "100%",
    "option4": "75%",
    "option5": 1,
    "correct_option": "NABARD is largely government-owned with 99.6% of its shares held by the Government of India.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "question": "The headquarters of the ‘United Nations World Tourism Organization’ is situated in:",
    "option1": "Madrid, Spain",
    "option2": "Gland, Switzerland",
    "option3": "Washington DC, USA",
    "option4": "Paris, France",
    "option5": 1,
    "correct_option": "The UNWTO headquarters is located in Madrid, Spain.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "question": "West Bengal legislative assembly consists of how many seats?",
    "option1": "292",
    "option2": "294",
    "option3": "296",
    "option4": "298",
    "option5": 2,
    "correct_option": "The West Bengal Legislative Assembly has a total of 294 seats.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 35,
    "question": "Which of the following country has been elected as President of the International Solar Alliance?",
    "option1": "USA",
    "option2": "Russia",
    "option3": "India",
    "option4": "Japan",
    "option5": 3,
    "correct_option": "India has been elected as President of the International Solar Alliance.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 36,
    "question": "Recently, Hawker Culture of which country has been inscribed on the UNESCO's Representative List of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Humanity?",
    "option1": "Indonesia",
    "option2": "China",
    "option3": "Vietnam",
    "option4": "Singapore",
    "option5": 1,
    "correct_option": "Indonesia's Hawker Culture was inscribed on UNESCO's Intangible Cultural Heritage list.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 37,
    "question": "The Chairman of the National Disaster Management Authority (NDMA) is____.",
    "option1": "National Security Advisor",
    "option2": "Prime Minister of India",
    "option3": "Chief of DRDO",
    "option4": "Home Minister of India",
    "option5": 1,
    "correct_option": "The NDMA is headed by the National Security Advisor of India.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 38,
    "question": "Which payment gateway company has decided to close its operation in India?",
    "option1": "MobiKwik",
    "option2": "Razor pay",
    "option3": "PayPal",
    "option4": "Lazypay",
    "option5": 3,
    "correct_option": "PayPal has decided to shut down its domestic payment operations in India.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 39,
    "question": "The Foxconn of toy world to set up India's first toy cluster in ____",
    "option1": "Madhya Pradesh",
    "option2": "Karnataka",
    "option3": "Kerala",
    "option4": "Rajasthan",
    "option5": 2,
    "correct_option": "India’s first toy cluster by Foxconn is being set up in Karnataka.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 40,
    "question": "Maradona scored 'hand of god' goal against which country?",
    "option1": "Germany",
    "option2": "France",
    "option3": "Portugal",
    "option4": "England",
    "option5": 4,
    "correct_option": "Diego Maradona scored the 'Hand of God' goal against England in the 1986 World Cup.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 41,
    "question": "Mutual Funds are regulated in the country by",
    "option1": "IRDAI",
    "option2": "Association of Mutual Funds of India (AMFI)",
    "option3": "NABARD",
    "option4": "Securities and Exchange Board of India",
    "option5": 4,
    "correct_option": "Mutual Funds in India are regulated by SEBI to ensure transparency and protect investors.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 42,
    "question": "Renowned personality Ustad Ghulam Mustafa Khan passed away recently, he was a veteran _____.",
    "option1": "Flute Maestro",
    "option2": "Tabla Maestro",
    "option3": "Sitar Maestro",
    "option4": "Classical Musician",
    "option5": 4,
    "correct_option": "Ustad Ghulam Mustafa Khan was a legendary classical musician in India.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 43,
    "question": "Which company has ranked first most-valued IT services brand globally, according to a report by Brand Finance?",
    "option1": "Accenture",
    "option2": "IBM",
    "option3": "Tata Consultancy Services (TCS)",
    "option4": "Infosys",
    "option5": 3,
    "correct_option": "TCS has been ranked as the most-valued IT services brand globally according to Brand Finance.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 44,
    "question": "Which of the following Asian countries has Nikkei as its stock market index?",
    "option1": "China",
    "option2": "Singapore",
    "option3": "Japan",
    "option4": "South Korea",
    "option5": 3,
    "correct_option": "Nikkei is the stock market index for Japan.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  },
  {
    "id": 45,
    "question": "The ‘ICC Men’s T20I Cricketer of the Decade’ has been awarded to?",
    "option1": "Virat Kohli",
    "option2": "Kane Williamson",
    "option3": "Steve Smith",
    "option4": "Rashid Khan",
    "option5": 1,
    "correct_option": "Virat Kohli was named the ICC Men’s T20I Cricketer of the Decade.",
    "explanation": 0,
    "count": 0
  }
]